Do you remember this diagram from lesson one? The adapter
has a reference to the raw data. And has instructions on
how to build each list item layout. These layouts eventually make
it into the list view here. But what happens if any
of this data changes. Let's say for example, there's a fourth
contact named Don. The adapter knows how to create a list
item layout for Don. But now the list view is outdated
because it only has three items. Somehow, we need the adapter.
To notify the list view that things have
changed. And lucky for us, there's a method
called: adapter.notifyDatasetChanged( ). This notifies any attached observers,
like this one, that the underlying adapter data has
changed. Then the list view needs to populate
its children again. So it asks the adapter
how many items there are? And the adapter
responds with four. Then the ListView goes and fetches
each one individually until it fills up the screen.
And it's through that method that the ListView is able
to get all its list items. But now you
must be thinking. How did we actually update the ListView
successfully, without adding this line of code in our
app? Well, with a ray adapter, whenever you add or
remove elements from it, it internally calls notifyDataSetChanged. That means
we don't have to do anything. But how can be
confirm this? Well, we can check the actual implementation
of the ArrayAdapter class in the framework. And here's
the code for the ArrayAdapter class within the Android
framework. You can follow along with the link below.
First, we're going to search for the Add method. Remember,
we added forecast strings. To the adapter using this
method. And sure enough we see that, the notify
data set changed method is called internally. But you
might be thinking what about this Boolean here. Well
let's look it up. If you scroll to the top
you'll see that, notify on change is declared as
true initially. As you go through your other references you'll
see that it's only changed here. In this set
notify on change method. Since we don't call this public
method, with the value false, then we know that we're
going to be safely notified each time the adapter updates.
Now let's go back to the add method. I want to
show you one more thing. You'll notice in the add
all method, it only notifies its observers once. Whereas in
the add method every time you call this it will update
it's observers. That means that our code actually is refreshing
the list every time. So, if you're targeting honeycomb of above
you can use this method to be a little more
efficient. In general don't be afraid to try and do this
on your own. As a general pro tip, if you're ever unsure about something,
feel free to go and check the
Android source code. Don't treat the framework code
like a black box. Take advantage of the fact that Android is open source. The
more you learn about the platform the
better of an Android developer you can become.